Heat. Heat.
Wow.
[Music]
Heat. Heat.
Heat.
[Music]
Good evening, good day everybody and
welcome to the Ask a Bidget show. Today
we are doing episode 268. It's been a
long journey but here we are and a even
longer way to go and today I'm going to
be taking questions that you all have
asked in the comments. Okay, we're
reverting to that original format and
we're going to do more of that going
forward. So I'm going to take questions
from the from the comments and then if
there is some time I'll I may take a few
questions at the end from the live chat.
So let's see who all is there on the
live chat with us. I can see Shiva Sai
Dave Davik Shrian Mr. Jam Jikshit Ha
Sundar Samarati Kumar Kanesh Mandicor
Amisha Mishra Mr. Saxa, Supratim, Dutta,
uh, Shivasai, Sam the Gamer, Latangi,
Suresh, Chat, DSP, Anonymous Scientist,
Bonjour, Mos, uh, Rana G, Shiva Sai, uh,
who else do we have? nationalist
uh yati 24 purusham pradan geopolitical
dub from indor mira that's a good name
sfc kumar kesh kahul dunak yati 24
unknown wamshi kale chiak patel
bashishta prrenal from kolkata yatinda
chiak pateli abi abhishek shvastav
uh who else do we have ajinka pawar
shashank sharma
Om Vidant Jadav
and so many other people maven is there
Jam Mr. Mcloven
and everybody else. So uh let's get
going with the questions. I won't be
able to greet you all but let's start
with the questions that we have. So
what's question number one?
Okay, question number one is by multiple
people and it's it's even more people
who have asked this question. Space
Striker Retesh Sharma Shar Kharki. We
should we should ignore words and focus
on actions. The Indian government is
loud in words against Pakistan but their
actions like allowing Pakistani YouTube
channels sent out a different message.
Is the government really nationalistic?
Why has the Indian government unbanned
Pakistani YouTube channels and Insta
accounts? What's the rationale behind
this move? Yesterday the Indian
government unblocked all Pakistani
propagandist accounts in YouTube and
Instagram. And today they are making a
childish claim that accounts got
unplugged because of some technical
glitch. Why does this government fear
too much in taking decisions etc. And
even if very important for the Indian
interests
when it comes to actions versus words I
think uh operation synindur was actions
those missiles raining down on Pakistani
air bases and uh military sites was
actions. The loitering drones the har
drones going down on Pakistani military
installations was actions. So let's not
say that the government is only words
and no actions. Let's that's not the
case at all. Okay. Now when it comes to
this matter about the YouTube channels
and possibly Instagram accounts, I heard
myself that yesterday some Pakistani
channels that had been banned were
unbanned for a while. I'm not sure about
the Instagram accounts. So let's take a
look at what's what the situation is. U
we are aware of a whole bunch of
Pakistani YouTube channel. I think many
Pakistani YouTube channels were very
popular in India because of the cricket
content. For example, Inzam, right?
Inam, the former cricket captain. In
Zamam, Inamama. Okay, Inzam
uh YouTube. So, what's the situation
with Mr. Inam? It says it's unavailable
now. So, let's uh keep an eye on that,
right? So, let's try and understand
scenarios. Scenarios. Always look at
scenarios. Let's not jump to
conclusions.
In case you watch my geost strategy
series, you will understand that you
have to look at the world from the
perspective of scenarios. What's the
most likely explanation? What's a less
likely explanation? What's a very highly
unlikely explanation? And so on. So
let's understand, let's explore some
scenarios.
Okay. uh the government had banned a
bunch of Pakistani accounts, YouTube
accounts, Twitter accounts, possibly
Instagram accounts. I'm not sure of
that. Okay. And it's because they spread
misinformation. For example, that that
fellow Aidi right Shahid Fredi, he is a
virulently anti-India guy. He I know
that in the past several Indian
cricketers like Mr. Harbajan Singh, Mr.
Ibra Singh etc have gone out of their
way to support him and so on. But that's
the deal with cricketers and sports
people. They don't understand the
national interest possibly but yes
people like Afidi etc have been banned
were banned now one hears that yesterday
or day before or whenever it was a
number of these YouTube channels became
visible in India
and now if you look it looks like they
are banned again. So then the question
is what happened? We clearly had banned
these channels these accounts. The
question is in what manner were they
banned? I mean what was the methodology
of implementing the bans?
One way of implementing a ban is that
the government can issue a directive an
order to Indian internet providers to
block certain well channels and so on.
Usually it's at the platform level but
you can I suppose also do it at the at
the channel level. So in case some uh
internet providers in India may have uh
perhaps you know undone that that could
explain it but maybe not the case. Maybe
this was done at the platform level. So
in that case what happens is that the
government of India goes and approaches
let's say platform X, platform Y,
platform Zed, YouTube, Twitter,
Instagram and tells them that we are
ordering you to block these accounts in
India. These should not be available in
India and the reasons are national
security. You don't get to ask us what
the reasons are. You will simply comply
with our directives and then YouTube
goes ahead and blocks Afredi and Inam
and whoever else. Okay? And uh Twitter
does the same thing and Instagram also
does the same thing. In that case, if
that is the case, then the action is
taken at the level of the platform which
is either YouTube or Instagram or
Twitter or whoever else. Okay. Now, in
case something happened yesterday and
some accounts became available again.
Now then we have
for example I just showed you right I
searched for for Inam on YouTube right
over here and YouTube is giving us a
message that this content is available
in this unavailable in the country
because of government orders and so on
so forth right so it means that YouTube
has implemented the ban within India
because of the government of India and
what the government of India has
directed them to do. So YouTube is
responsible for doing this. So in case
some accounts were unbanned yesterday,
maybe YouTube maybe whoever whoever else
then I can think of two scenarios maybe
three. Scenario one is that YouTube or
Twitter or whoever they decided to unban
these accounts for reasons best known to
them in the absence of any Indian
government directive to unban them.
That's one possibility. That's one
scenario. Well, that well it's their
platform. They can do whatever they
like, right? That's one possibility we
have to think of. Another possibility
this is these are all hypothetical
possibilities and scenarios. I'm not
saying this happened or that happened.
I'm giving you scenarios, plausible
scenarios, hypothetical plausible
scenarios. So scenario A is that the
platforms
maybe independently maybe under the
directions of their government or maybe
something else for whatever reason the
platforms decided to unblock certain
accounts. That's one scenario.
Second scenario is maybe somebody from
India itself directed the platforms to
unblock the accounts. That's also a
plausible scenario. Maybe somebody who
works for the government of India and
who's who's in charge of inter
interacting interfacing with these
platforms. Maybe somebody from that team
perhaps one person perhaps
hypothetically
hypothetically may have done that.
That's another scenario to think of and
then maybe maybe hypothetically when
there was a backlash from the from the
viewers in India then the then somebody
at a higher level in the government may
have realized what's happened and they
may have reinforced and and
re-implemented this. So there are
multiple scenarios. I can think of even
more scenarios. The point is something
happened and action was taken I think
reasonably fast
and then these uh channels Pakistani uh
accounts and channels have been as far
as I know blocked again in India. So
whatever happened the government of
India needs to look into it. I suppose
they would be aware whether it is the
platforms taking action on their own.
Maybe somebody from the government of
India hypothetically may have quietly
told the platforms that you know go
ahead and open it up again possibly
hypothetically or maybe something else.
So whatever the cause is then look into
it and address
address the root cause. If it is some
hypothetically rogue employee
hypothetically some some person at at
some level in the government of India
who went and told the the platforms that
you can we you're okay to allow this to
to be available in India again then that
hypothetical employee or bureaucrat
needs to needs to be well possibly
disciplined or whatever maybe it's
something else maybe it's something else
we don't know what it is my point is
let's not jump to conclusions
and start blaming the government of
India. Okay, there could be lots of
reasons why this happened. At the end of
the day, please remember these are
foreign platforms. These are not really
under our control. They will comply with
the government of India directives as
long as you keep on giving the
directives. But if uh you take your eyes
off the ball, then you may get clean
bold or you may get stumped. So you got
to always keep the eyes on the ball. And
these things will happen as long as
you're not in control of the thing,
right? So if if it's a foreign platform,
you don't really control it. Uh so
that's that's uh the way I see it. Uh I
would not say that the government of
India has unblocked it. Okay. Whatever
had happened, the unblocking was done at
at the level of the platforms, not at
the level of the government of India.
The government of India doesn't control
the platforms. The government of India
doesn't uh put on, you know, control the
onoff switch.
So somewhere something happened and uh
it was noticed reasonably fast and the
bans have been re-implemented which is
good to see and I'm sure that the
government of India will have understood
what happened what went wrong. They
would have looked into it. I'm sure
that's not a twoe investigation with a
with a with a committee. I'm sure it it
can be done pretty fast and appropriate
action should be taken if if at whatever
level it needs to be taken. I am not
saying that it was this cause or that
cause or cause A or scenario B or
scenario C or whatever whatever it is
needs to be addressed. That is how I see
it. Let's not jump to conclusions. Let's
not start blaming the government when
you don't control the platform. This is
what happens. So my point is we need to
have our own indigenous platforms. Well,
that's a whole different story, isn't
it? My offense. Okay, question two.
Question two is about F-35 uh the the
F-35 saga. So we have a F-35,
a UK, a British F-35 which is currently
parked in in what tuan
wherever it is parked and it's been
there for like 3 weeks now and uh it
appears that it's not in a flyable
condition anymore and it's going to have
to be potentially dismantled and shipped
to the UK and the UK will obviously uh
foot the bill of the parking charges and
whatever other charges are
So the question is what was so we have
two questions one by Premar one by
Anikit. Uh Premar says, "Is it not
possible to get the stealth material of
F-35 as it is in rain and with sample of
the ground around it? We can get what
material is used to coat the thing." And
Aniket says, "What was this British F-35
doing near the Indian coastline? Are
conspiracy theories true? I'm not sure
what these are. Or is it a bad or was it
just a bad weather malfunction?" Let's
address an question first. uh what was
this uh aircraft doing near the Indian
coastline? So we had I I believe we held
some uh joint exercises, naval exercises
between the Indian military and the UK
military, Indian Navy, UK military uh UK
Navy, two navies worked together for a
bit for a joint exercise or something
and that's why we had this uh uh British
aircraft carrier of the Indian coastline
in international waters of course and
that's why this uh F-35 was flying
around because it was part it was it was
based on that aircraft carrier. which
was in the vicinity and maybe it was
doing training sorties or whatever.
Okay. Uh so it was flying and it there
was obviously heavy weather. Right now
it's the rainy season in the
subcontinent. So you have very heavy
weather, lots of rain and uh they say
that the F-35 attempted multiple u times
to land on the aircraft carrier did not
work out and it was running short of
fuel. So it had to make an emergency
landing in
in the Indian airport, Indian air base.
Uh, and ever since then, it's been
parked over there. So, the question then
arises that once it landed, why couldn't
it just be refueled and sent on its way?
Go back. Go back. Right. But for some
reason, it's not gone back. And I don't
I'm not sure what the stories are, but
now the now the news, what I hear in the
news is that it's not in a flyable
condition. It's there's something wrong
with it. It's malfunctioning or
something. You can't fly it. that's
going to have to be apparently
dismantled and shipped to the UK and
obviously the UK will pay the bill for
all of that. Uh so that's what one hears
and of course there have been conspiracy
theories about uh maybe it's a spy
aircraft and they've got lots of sensors
inside the aircraft hidden inside to spy
on the Indian uh on the in the Indian
military capabilities in that airport
that air base. Uh I'm I'm not sure what
what is true, what is not. I'm um you
know in the absence of sufficient
information all you can do is speculate
and speculation can lead you in all
kinds of directions including into what
you call conspiracy theory directions. I
don't know. Uh it's possible that you it
could have had some spying spying
devices sensors of some kind kinds etc.
It's the possibility exists but I'm not
sure really sure what the thing is. I am
not here to sensationalize the issue and
say that you know
and all that nonsense right we don't
know it's a possibility that we have to
take seriously but it may not be the
only possibility like I said multiple
scenarios one can you know imagine for
what happened here as well so the thing
is that this exists here and it's it's
under uh under under heavy security I
suppose one CRPF officer with uh
automatic rifle standing near it that's
what you
and so on. So that's how I say it. Uh
I'm sure the government knows better.
I'm sure the government of India knows
exactly what was being done there. Okay?
Whether it was really a malfunction or
whether it was on a spying mission or
whatever else. I'm not even sure what
happened to the pilot. Uh the pilot
obviously was he repatriated? Was it
sent back to the aircraft carrier? Was
he sent put on a plane and sent back to
London? What happened? I'm not really
sure. But obviously the pilot is not
here after 3 weeks. So something so the
government of India is fully aware of
what's going on. I'm pretty sure now
about the stealth material.
Uh so it I what I hear is that the the
F-35 it has a stealth coating, a special
coating of a special material and you've
got to repaint it after every mission.
That's what one hears. Okay. So when
you're doing training missions, you
don't need to repaint every time it
lands on the aircraft carrier. But when
you're on an actual combat mission and
you go and do your thing and whatever
else you're supposed to do and you
return, then it has to be repainted all
over again. It has to be given a new
coating of this stealth material. That's
what I hear. And that's one of the
reasons why the flying costs are so
high. And the downtime between missions
is also so long, like 50 hours at least
for the time it takes to to paint the
thing and for the paint to dry and all
that. So it looks like uh it has a very
special stealth coating
now. The the aircraft has been here for
3 weeks roughly give or take and it's
been raining. So is it possible that the
rain could have dissolved or some of the
the coating material or some of it could
be found in the puddles around the
airport around the aircraft? I think
it's possible.
So does it mean that we should just go
and collect the the puddle water the
rain water and uh do a proper chemical
analysis of that whatever analysis and
find out what material they're using.
It's something that certainly can be
done. It's the thing something we should
possibly do take take it seriously pos
perhaps. Uh but we also have to consider
the possibility that this was an
aircraft on a training mission. It must
have done lots of training sorties and
maybe the stealth coating wasn't present
on it
cuz they want look I think if if there's
a there's a chance that the aircraft
will end up in India with the stealth
coating and the Indians will find out
what the stealth coating is I think then
given that possibility they would
actually have preferred to ditch the
aircraft in the in the water in the
ocean and let it let it sink because
it's a very very
uh secret
secret material, right? It's it's not
something they would want their uh you
know nonallies to get get their hands
on. Uh so I would say certainly we
should go and sample the puddle water
and see if we can find some traces of
some special substance. If we find it,
fantastic. I I am not opposed to that at
all. I actually would welcome it. But I
would say that you know it's it's more
likely that uh the aircraft was not
coated with the material since it was on
training. So it is not on combat
missions. It's only on combat missions
that you coat it with that special
substance. On on training missions you
you typically don't do that. There's no
need for for that. Um that's how I see
it. Uh it was on a training mission and
so on. And and do remember that the
Indian government, Indian military,
whoever it was, they put out a tweet
saying that it was the aircraft was
detected and and and something other
something or the other. So they made it
a point to they very pointedly tweeted
that we detected the aircraft. It would
indicate that maybe the aircraft was not
in stealth mode at the time. It was not
coated with it special substance and
maybe some other it was also it it also
had missiles and bombs or whatnot
attached to the wings which obviously
increases the radar cross-section and so
on. So you know that's that's how I see
it. Um they can certainly try and and
sample the puddle water the rain water
and see if they can find something but
most likely they will not find
something. Okay but no harm trying
definitely.
Ajit ja creator says what's your take on
the F-35 India deal as Trump is
reportedly forcing India to buy it.
Really? Trump is forcing us to buy it.
Yeah. Really?
I don't think we're going to buy that
piece of
um that aircraft. Uh what what's what's
the term I used in the past? Flying
trash can. The F-35 is a terrible
aircraft. But that's not the reason we
should not buy it. See, what's my take
on the F-35? My F-35 deal. There is no
F-35 deal. I don't think India will be
purchasing the F-35 no matter what
happens. especially after Trump's
behavior towards India uh his his
championing of Pakistan his his great
love for Pakistan newfound love for
Pakistan uh his interference in India
Pakistan bilateral issues his uh
interference in operation zindur after
all that he has done uh there's the
price that he's going to have to pay for
this and one thing is for sure we will
not be purchasing the F-35 if India ends
up purchasing the F-35 it it means that
we are on our way to vasalhood it means
that we have given in to the Americans.
I I don't think it's going to happen.
But my the question really is is is that
why am I opposed to the F-35 deal? It's
not like I have some some some kind of
animosity towards country X or country
Y. I have nothing personal against the
US. It's a wonderful nation and greatest
nation in the world, most powerful
nation, etc. No question. Then why do I
oppose India potentially purchasing the
F-35? Well, I oppose that on on the
issue of sovereignty.
Then you will ask but we bought the
Rafal, we bought the Sukoy, we bought
the make whatever. Where is what about
sovereignty? Well, you need to grow up a
little and understand what I mean by
sovereignty.
See,
when you buy something, let's say I
purchase a pen, a pen, okay? I purchase
a pen. So when once I purchase it, this
becomes mine, right? It it is supposed
to become my instrument. And I'm
supposed to be able to do whatever I
want with it. I can write, I can sketch,
I can draw, I can uh whatever. Yeah,
it's it's entirely up to me what I use
this for. Now, the the deal with the
F-35 or any US platform
is that if you purchase the goddamn
thing, it's not really yours.
And it has liabilities. It comes with
liabilities. First of all, you don't get
the full version. you get an export
version which is a stripped down dumped
down version of the aircraft. Secondly,
the Americans will decide how it'll be
used. So every day before you you take
it out for a spin in the skies, you
essentially have to get an OTP from the
Americans.
Okay? Essentially like that. And and to
get the OTP, you have to first give them
your flight path and your flight plan
and all that. So once they go through
your flight plan and what you're
planning to do, then they will say,
"Okay, it's fine." And you they give you
the OTP.
Then you enter the OTP and the aircraft
powers on. Then you can only do what
you're allowed to do. Okay? And then the
aircraft may have builtin kill switches.
Now, is it something is it some some
imaginary concept I've pulled out of my
backside? A kill switch? Is it is it so?
Ask the Australians
whether they believe in kill switches or
not. There are many experts you know
very respected experts in India who are
saying that this this kill ski kill
switch business is nonsense. What is the
skill switch nonsense? Kill switch
garbage. It's a figment of some idiots's
imagination. They say h ask the
Australians what happened to the the the
aircraft they purchased from the US in
the 1980s.
They purchased a bunch of I think F-15s
or whatever it was,
okay, in the 1980s. And once they
purchased and they acquired, they got
they took delivery of the aircraft. The
Australians, remember Australia is one
of the five eyes nations. It is one of
America's closest vasals. The Americans
the Australians take delivery of these
aircraft in the 1980s. They take them
for a spin and they say, "Okay, let's
see what these what these beasts are
capable of." So they do some uh mock
drills in which they uh designate some
targets and they the pilots will then
tell the aircraft okay lock onto this
target and take it out. So the moment
they try to do that the aircraft's
target acquisition system simply ignored
the pilot's directives.
It refused to lock on to targets that
were not preapproved by the Americans.
And this happened over and over again.
The aircraft were useless.
The aircraft were useless. The
Australians could not use them for what
whatever purposes they intended them
from for and it was all overridden. The
pilots directives were all overridden by
the software in the aircraft. And it was
not until the 21st century, the first or
second decade of the 21st century that
the Australians were able to crack that
software. So for 30 years, the aircraft
were useless for the Australians. Okay,
that's just one example of a kill
switch. What you call a kill switch?
Kill switch means you you can prevent
the aircraft from taking X action or Y
action. In the extremist cases, it may
even refuse to power on. Obviously, the
OTP also comes into effect over there,
right?
And uh and then there could be back
doors and first of all you to to fly the
F-35 you have to sign all kinds of
agreements that open up your airwaves to
the Americans to make your uh your
electronics communications compatible to
compatible with American whatever
standards and all. So that again you
know you lose you lose some sovereignty
there. Then if you acquire a whole bunch
of aircraft $110 million a piece and you
can't use them for what you want to use
them for and maybe they're also you know
siphoning off your electronics
communications and relaying them
somewhere. What what happens to your
sovereignty? There's no sovereignty. You
become a basal like this. U and and
there's so much more. They could have
back doors that would transmit all your
data, all your all your classified
secret information back to the Pentagon.
So much more. This is not science
fiction. This is routine. This is
routine. Okay. So, if you acquire this
aircraft, you essentially hand over your
sovereignty on a platter to the
Americans, your military sovereignty. Uh
and and it's at the end of the day, it's
just not just that not good. It's not a
good aircraft at all. Uh I would say
look, if Trump wants to sell aircraft to
India, we would we should ask for the
F-22.
We want the F-22, not the F-35. Let's
see what Trump has to say. You want us
to buy American aircraft? Sure. All
right, sir. We want the F-22.
Now, let's see what Mr. Trump has to
say. He's going to throw a tantrum. No,
F22 blah blah blah. It's not the best
aircraft in the world. F-35 is the one
on offer and so on. So, my point is
F-35, we should not acquire it no matter
what Trump says, how many tantrums he
throws and so on.
Pranay Paul says, "How has the Dalai
Lama's reincarnation decision rattled
China? What's the core reason behind
Beijing's visible irritation this time?"
Oh my goodness, Beijing is irritated. I
am so sad. Okay, before we go into the
matter, let us let me remind you all
that I have been very clear and very
consistent about my stand when it comes
to the Dalai Lama's his holiness, the
Dalai Lama's reincarnation. And in case
because memories are short, let me just
put this on the record one more time. I
did it yesterday. I'm doing it again
today. Take a look at this. He needs to
announce his plans for his reincarnation
because the Chinese plan to hijack the
office of the Dalai Lama and appoint
their own Dalai Lama. So if his holiness
the Dalai Lama announces that he will
not be reincarnated in Tibet, he will be
reincarnated reincarnated either in
India or somewhere else then the Chinese
claim to the legitimacy of their
appointee as the Dalai Lama will
evaporate. His holiness the Dalai Lama
is now at the stage where he needs to
decide about his succession. Who's going
to be the next Dalai Lama? Will he
reincarnate in Chinese occupied Tibet or
will he reincarnate in the diaspora
outside of Tibet? So this is the
succession the Chinese are worried about
because they want to appoint their own
Dalai Lama and if the current Dalai Lama
says that that is illegitimate then the
Chinese attempt to hijack the
institution of the Dalai Lama will fail.
The 11th Panchchan Lama they hijack that
institution. So once he passes on the
Chinese government will hijack that
process and they will appoint a CCP
Dalai Lama a Chinese Communist Party
sanctioned Dalai Lama. It is something
that is important from multiple
perspectives including a geopolitical
perspective. The Dalai Lama needs to
announce I mean he needs to make his
intentions clear whether he does intend
to be reincarnated or not. Eventually
whenever the India China issue will be
resolved the root cause is Tibet the
Chinese the illegal illegitimate brutal
Chinese occupation of Tibet. I think it
is high time for his holiness the the
Dalai Lama to uh declare what is the
succession going to be like. The Dalai
Lama successor has to be non-Chinese.
Ideally what his holiness should do is
he should make a clear unambiguous
declaration of how the success the issue
of the succession should be handled.
So there we have it. So it's clear that
I have been extremely consistent on this
and I have I have uh been suggesting
recommending that this decision be taken
and that is exactly what's happened. So
what I've been saying for the for more
than four years it has finally happened
now on the eve of the Dalai Lama his
holiness the Dalai Lama's 90th birthday.
So it's excellent. And now the question
is what Prane is asking how has this
decision about his reincarnation how has
it rattled China? What's the core reason
behind Beijing's visible irritation this
time? You haven't seen the irritation
yet. They're just starting off. Are they
going to throw a lot of tantrums? The
the Chinese which is fine. U
how does it matter what is Mr. Xinping's
mood at this moment or tomorrow morning?
That is their problem. That's not our
problem. Uh now the question is about
the reincarnation thing. So what is it
first of all? what is the matter of the
Dalai Lama of the Dalai Lama's
reincarnation and what does that have to
do with geopolitics and India China
relations. So if you want to understand
in detail you should watch yesterday's
episode of geost strategy in which I've
gone into this in great detail but
overall the the see Tibet is is under
illegal Chinese occupation the Chinese
annex next Tibet in the 1950s after
invading it with the help of Shri the
magnificent Shri Neuji uh and and they
have devastated Tibet they they have
tried to conduct an demic cultural and
ethnic genocide of of the Tibetans and
so on. uh now the reincarnation issue is
that the Chinese would like to appoint
the next Dalai Lama. So the next Dalai
Lama if if everything goes according to
China will be
a member of the Chinese Communist Party
a party that doesn't belong belong
believe in God in religion in
spirituality they want to appoint the
next Dalai Lama it's a tradition that
goes back five six centuries and they
want to decide who the next Dalai Lama
will be so that they can take over
control of the entire spiritual world of
the Buddhists the Dalai Lama is the
highest ranking spiritual leader of all
Buddhists, right? And the the Chinese
would want would like to own that.
And if this matter of the reincarnation
and the appointment of the next Dalai
Lama happens outside of Chinese control,
then it indicates very clearly to the to
the entire world that this matter is
beyond China's control. And this matter
which is central to Tibetan culture is
not in China's control which raises
questions about the legitimacy of
China's occupation of Tibet.
So this matter essentially reopens the
Tibet issue. This matter once again uh
ends up categorizing Tibet as a disputed
area, a disputed territory and that's
why this has rattled China.
So um in case you don't know the Dalai
Lama reincarnates
okay uh according to our culture dharmic
culture we believe in reincarnation
Tibetan culture is Dharmic culture it is
also our culture okay it's also an
extension of our culture so the Dalai
Lama reinc once the Dal Dalai Lama
passes away and leaves his body uh he
reincarnates in the form of a of a of a
young child a boy And that child will
show certain signs and characteristics
that have that have that are wellnown.
And Tibetan ladas go across the country
across Tibet looking for a child that
has those characteristics. And once they
find the child, they bring the child to
Lassa to Potala Palace and um train the
child to become the next Dalai Lama. And
the child is obviously the
reincarnation. So the child will
possibly remember some of it. and so on.
That's that's the uh the tradition. Now,
Patala Palace is under Chinese Communist
Party occupation. So, it can't happen in
Patala Palace. So, now it'll happen in
Dhamshala.
The next Dalai Lama, the 15th, the
current Dalai Lama is the 14th Dalai
Lama. He whenever he chooses, he's going
to be 90 years old soon. So, whenever he
chooses, I I hope he lives the longest
life. Maybe 100 110 years as long as
humanly humanly possible. But whenever
it is time for him as per his choice, he
will leave his body and reincarnate
reincarnate. And now he has decreed that
he is not going to be the reincarnation
will process the reincarnation process
and and and identification process of
the next Dalai Lama will proceed as per
tradition and without any external
interference which means it will happen
outside of Chinese occupied Tibet. Which
means it will most likely Which means
that most likely the next Dalai Lama
will be chosen from a newborn child from
within the Tibetan diaspora in most
likely India. Which means that Dham
Salah will be the center of Tibetan
Buddhism. It will not be under Chinese
control and it will raise enormous
questions about the legitimacy of
China's illegal occupation of Tibet. And
that's why this is a disaster for China.
Right? That's that's what explains the
tantrums China is throwing and is going
to throw even more.
And what does this signal? It signals
that the government of India has taken a
taken a decision now that there's no
possibility of any any any raosimo any
any whatever with China
and the Chinese it means that the
government of India has realized that
the Chinese have a decision that they're
going to throw all their weight behind
Pakistan and so on and they're going to
be openly hostile to India. So now it
looks like that's that's the realization
that's happened in India and his
holiness as a consequence has made his
announcement. He could have made it
before earlier later whenever but I
think it was decided at some point in
time that he would make the announcement
uh around his 90th birthday. So he has
made the announcement. So what were the
choices that he had? One one indication
he had given a few years ago is was that
maybe he would not reincarnate at all.
they would simply attain nirvana. A
person of his uh of his stature I
suppose they have the option of simply
uh walking away from the cycle of uh
birth and death rebirth and just attain
Nirvana and move on. So the Dalai Lama
institution will then would possibly
then have either ended or possibly
become an elected office. But now he has
made it very clear that he will
reincarnate and the reincarnation
process will happen outside of Chinese
control and so on. So that is why China
is so upset
because they would like to control
everything when it comes to Tibet. And
the central central thing about Tibet is
the institution of the Dalai Lama the
most revered figure in Buddhism
and that now is going to all happen from
Dham Shala. So that will from a Chinese
materialistic perspective okay from
their perspective it will give India
tremendous legitimacy
across the Buddhist world. we are
already the the center of Hinduism. I
mean anywhere in the world where you
have Hindus if they want to go to a
pilgrimage they come to India right uh
when it comes to Buddhism the pilgrimage
places are obviously Bodhaya where where
uh Bhagwan Buddha attained Nirvana it's
Lumbini which is Nepal and it is also
Lassa because that's where the highest
authority uh spiritual authority of of
Buddhism used to reside so now it's all
going to be India and from China's
materialistic perspective g you that
sort of perspective narrow perspective
it will give India a tremendous amount
of soft power over all the Buddhist
countries it will make India the leader
of not just the Hindu world but also the
Buddhist world essentially the entire
dharmic world and that's something China
doesn't want and also it it raises big
questions about the legitimacy of
China's illegal occupation of Tibet so
all of these factors are what have
rattled China it doesn't look like they
were expecting this would happen but
here it is it's happened and uh yeah
There's going to be a long set of
repercussions of this. Uh and if you
want to understand what those are, watch
yesterday's uh episode of geost strategy
in which I have gone into this in great
detail.
Uh two more questions about his holiness
the the Dai Lama and the whole matter.
Is India t taking an aggressive position
against China in the context of Tibet?
Is this a good idea especially when we
should be keeping our heads down and
avoiding conflicts? And as per your
prediction, India, China relations will
go downhill after the the Dalai Lama
episode. But will it be in India's
interest as this is happening when India
US relations are also in bad shape?
Look,
look at China's actions over the past
few days and weeks and months. Have they
been friendly towards India?
They have not been friendly towards
India. They've been hostile actions.
There were Chinese troops in Pakistan
when um the terrorist attack in Pahelgam
happened right in Pakistan occupied
Kashmir. Not Pakistan but Pakistan
occupied Kashmir. Imagine China sending
troops to Pakistan occupied Kashmir our
territory which is illegally held by
Pakistan temporarily. Is that a friendly
act? No, it's not a friendly act. It's a
hostile act. So they were there the Pak
the Chinese troops in P when the
terrorist attack happened. The Chinese
troops were also there when operation
synindur happened the three-day war
between India and Pakistan. The Chinese
have supplied weapons systems etc. Good
or bad doesn't matter but they have
supplied weapons and whatn not to to
Pakistan. They are saying that they will
supply F what J35s to to Pakistan right
uh they are taking the the side of
Pakistan in every matter. U they are
imposing sanctions on India. They've uh
banned the export of rare earth magnets
and other materials to India. They have
blocked the exports of uh specialized
fertilizers to India. They are imposing
economic sanctions on India. Do you
think these are all friendly actions?
They are already taking hostile actions.
The Chinese have made the decision that
they will not be friends with India for
some time. They were making you know
nice nice sounds that you know we need
to have a gapimo we need to have a dant
let's withdraw some troops here and
there that sort of thing but it's clear
that they are not serious so the
government of India has understood the
Chinese are not serious
so it makes no difference what happens
here the Chinese have already made the
choice so so it's fine so what we have
done is the right choice and it's
something I have been saying for the
longest time and So
look, it's like this. How long do you
keep appeasing the enemy?
Just by unilaterally showing good
behavior, does it mean that the enemy
will also show better behavior? Because
we are being humble and nice and we are
going out of our way to keep our head
down and so on. No, they will keep on
doing what they want to do. So at least
we are sending a signal to China that we
are also serious. We too can play the
game. And now we're going to be more
proactive after this step has been
taken. I assure you we're going to be
much more proactive towards China. It is
what it is. You have to deal with the
the adversary in in a various in a
variety of ways and this is uh the most
appropriate way in my opinion when it
comes to China. What we have done is
this.
We have reopened the Tibet issue.
We have essentially stated that Tibet is
a disputed territory. Tibet, China's
occupation of Tibet is not legitimate.
Do you know how the Chinese started
making claims over over Arunachal
Pradesh?
Initially
they were not claiming Arunachal.
It's in 2003 when the then Indian prime
minister
explicitly recognized China's
sovereignty over Tibet. That's when when
the Chinese got that that India no
longer disputes Tibet's status. That's
when they started making claims in
Arunachal.
I think it was in 2006 that the then
Chinese ambassador to India said that
the whole of Arunachal Pradesh is
Chinese territory because it is
apparently allegedly South Tibet and
because you yourselves have recognized
Tibet as part of China that's why
Arunachal should be also part of China.
That was their logic their rationale.
So by opening reopening Tibet and and
and signaling that we consider Tibet
disputed territory we are putting them
on the back foot which means that we're
telling them you want to play this game
we can play a bigger game because Tibet
is a much bigger ter territory and what
happens the matter that is the at the
core of of the Tibetan ethos the matter
of the Dalai Lama that is not in your
under your control and that tells the
world that you don't have sovereignty
over Tibet you're hold over Tibet is
illegit Tibet because the the Tibetan
diaspora doesn't uh recognize your you
know your your
the the doesn't recognize that you have
a legitimate claim over Tibet. You are
holding it illegally and that's why they
are doing the entire process of the
reincarnation of the Dalai Lama and the
selection and the and the identification
of the next Dalai Lama outside of China.
So I think it is the right thing to do.
I know that we have all kinds of uh
challenges that we face. Uh India US
relations aren't also great right now.
Not because of us but because of Mr.
Trump. But it doesn't mean that we
should give up and and not fight. So
here we are. We are fighting and that's
the right thing.
uh the Chinese involvement in Pakistani
defense operation during operation
synindur has everything to do in the
current development of his holiness
Dalai Lama's decision divine
intervention also I think it's it's one
thing that uh obviously made it very
clear to India that China is not serious
about uh better relations with India
since last year sometime since the
middle of 2024 the Chinese have been
indicating that they are interested in
better relations with India. We are
feeling the heat from the US and the US
is shutting down their markets for us.
Then where do we export? We need the
Indian market then because that's the
only big market left and that's why we
need better relations with you. So let's
be friends and let's pull back some
troops from the border regions and uh do
some confidence building measures and
blah blah blah. So there was all talk
talk talk word on the other hand they
were they were supporting Pakistan all
the time and that became very clear
during operation sindur. So obviously
the the the
uh whatever happened during operation
sindur and the Chinese position at the
time and the Chinese position and and uh
actions ever since they have gone a long
way towards uh indicating to us that the
Chinese have never been serious about
wanting better relations with India. So
since you don't want better relations
with us, well then why don't you go to
hell all the way. So yeah, that's where
we stand.
Rakkesh Mistri says, "I'm from
Bangladesh, watching your videos since
2023." Well, thank you so much for
watching. I hope you're well in
Bangladesh uh and so on. Yeah, thank you
so much. Thank you so much, sir. Uh you
said US and India, US and China talks
eye to eye. They see eye to eye. uh when
it comes to India, India's growth and
everything to do with India, my
questions are first of all, is it
possible that China and India see eye to
eye against American conspiracy? And
secondly, Russia, is it possible that uh
Russia and India could cooperate
together against Chinese aggression?
Okay. So yes, the Chinese and the
Americans do see eye to eye on two
things. They see essentially one thing
which and the second thing is an
extension of the first thing. Uh the
they see eye to eye when it comes to
India. Neither China nor the US wants
India to become a much larger economy.
Neither of these nations wants to see
India as a 10 trillion 15 trillion 20
trillion economy. They don't want that
because if India grows to a $10 trillion
economy, it will only happen if India
becomes a manufacturing tower and it
will only happen if other nations, their
companies pull out of China and move
into India and and essentially transfer
their manufacturing base from China to
India. That would be a disaster for
China clearly. So it's terrible for
China. It's actually an existential
threat for China, you see. So China
doesn't want India to grow and the US
also doesn't want India to grow too much
because then India could be could
potentially become the next China and
India may not have some of the problems
that China has and so on. India has
other problems, China has other problems
but some we may have learned from the
Chinese mistakes and so much more. So
the US also doesn't want India to become
a 10 trillion 15 trillion etc economy.
So both nations see eye to eye on that
matter. Because of that both nations the
US and China also see eye to eye on
Pakistan. Pakistan obviously east and
west Pakistan both are US vasals. Both
have underwent undergone regime change
operations. US
US mediated regime change operations.
Pakistan 2022 Imran Khan's ouster and
the and whoever else came into power was
a US wasal. And in East Pakistan
Bangladesh uh you had the regime change
operation which ousted Shri Kasina who
was pro India. And now you have a very
anti-India regime there which is a
military regime and the puppet is this
fellow called Yunus Muhammad Yunus Nobel
prize winner right and yet despite being
US vasals both east and west Pakistan
are also cooperating with China Muhammad
you know went to Beijing and he was
lecturing the the Chinese over there
that Bangladesh can cut off India's far
east northeast and make it a landlocked
place which is why you should invest in
Bangladesh and we are very good for you
and Pakistan also has been uh courting
the Chinese and the Chinese are also
courting Pakistan. So you can see that
the US is okay with East and West
Pakistan having uh dealings with China
despite the US regarding China as their
principal adversary.
So it's clear that the US and and China
see eye to eye when it comes to India
and they see eye to eye when it comes to
East and West Pakistan
to a significant extent.
Now let's let's take your questions. Uh
is it possible that China and India see
I2I against American conspiracy? Well,
there's no US conspiracy. The US deal is
that they want to keep on ruling the
world. They are the world's sole
superpower. They are an imperial power.
It's it's an empire and it's something
that threatens China. Obviously, the
Chinese see that as a threat. Uh the
Chinese want to retake Taiwan. The
Americans are so powerful that China
can't even take an island which is in
its own backyard. Um, and the US doesn't
want India to grow also. So maybe India
and China could work together. Well, it
doesn't work because China is a spoiler.
Essentially, what you're asking me is
about Russia, India, China, RAIC. And if
you see one of my previous geost
strategy episodes, I will I've shown
I've demonstrated that China is a
spoiler. China is a spoiler when it
comes to RAIC. China is a spoiler when
it comes to bricks. It is because of
China that bricks is not viable beyond
it is merely a symbolic organization and
it has some economic value but a apart
from that it's not a a viable strategic
block and neither is ra which has so
much potential because China is a
spoiler. China is not just a nation that
attempts to keep on bullying India. It
also keeps on attempting to bully Russia
in case you're not aware. all they they
they have consistently in the past
decade or so treated Russia like a
junior partner. Um
one of the blatant glaring examples is
China's ctographic
uh uh aggression towards Russia putting
out maps that show Russian territory as
Chinese and putting uh putting out maps
that uh give Chinese place names to
Russian places like Vladivosto and and
so on. The Chinese are playing the same
game with Russia the that they're
playing with India. They're claiming
Russian territory and they are looking
for ways and means to claim more Russian
territory and they will operationalize
this whenever they see they feel that
the time is right and that whenever they
feel that Russia is in a weak weak
position.
So India and China can't see eye to eye
they it's not possible because the
Chinese approach the Chinese attitude
and because of China's spoiler role
the Chinese end up bolstering American
primacy over the world. It's the last
thing they want to do. But they are so
short-sighted and their attitude is so
poor that through their behavior towards
India and Russia, they end up bolstering
American primacy over the world over and
over again. That is what is going to
lead to the downfall of China whenever
it happens. Okay? Their attitude they
have they will have nobody else but
themselves to blame.
And it's clear to us now and it's also
clear to Russia that China cannot be
trusted. See, Russia right now is in a
position where it has to rely on China
to to a very large extent and Russia is
genuinely in in danger of becoming a a
junior partner at least to China if not
an outright vasal. Mr. Putin won't allow
that to happen as far as I understand
but that's a clear and present danger
for Russia right uh
so Russia and India they have a lot in
common they have a common adversary
China they also have nothing uh that no
no friction points no pain points
because you know because of the way
things are so clearly it's very likely
that in the long run Russia and India
will cooperate
will work with each other when it comes
to countering Chinese aggression,
possibly containing China as far as
possible. Look, Russia has sold the S400
system to China, but they also sold it
to India. I assure you, the Chinese were
very unhappy when the Russians sold the
S400 to India, but it's fine. The
Russians were okay with the Chinese
displeasure. when it comes to the
Brahmos missile system which is
Indo-Russian
uh so whenever we sell the Brahmos
system to another country we need to
take the Russians on board and the
Russians have a veto in this I assure
you of that so if you want to sell it to
nation X but Russia doesn't like nation
X they can say no and we cannot sell it
we have that understanding with Russia
so we have sold the Brahmo system to
Chinese adversaries
okay Russia was okay with that China
obviously is displeased with that but it
is what it is. So Russia has been okay
with that. So we are actually indeed
seeing eye to eye when it comes to
cooperating against Chinese aggression
and Russia Russia would like nothing
more than India rising, India growing,
India becoming 10 trillion dollar
economy. That way they will have to rely
on China less. So Russia and India can
work together. India and China won't be
able to work together because of the
Chinese attitude. Very poor attitude,
self-defeating attitude. But one thing
both Russia and India understand is you
cannot trust China. The Chinese are not
trustworthy. They'll stab you in the
back at the first early the earliest
available opportunity.
Vashta says, "Wouldn't continuous slow
war with Ukraine decrease the military
weapons stockpiles that Russia has?
Isn't that a problem for Russia if
there's a future war with NATO?"
On the other I mean to the contrary to
the contrary um see it's clear that
Russia has adopted this slow war
strategy when it comes to Ukraine they
have adopted willingly adopted this
frozen conflict methodology when it
comes to Ukraine. Is Russia not capable
of overrunning Ukraine in a week's time?
It certainly is. Russia if it wants can
flatten Ukraine flatten Ukraine
tomorrow. They have the firepower to do
that but they have chosen not to do
that. If you remember in early 2022 the
the war the special military operation
began in I think February 22nd
of February 2022. Um and very soon you
had columns of Russian vehicles and
troops that had reached the outskirts of
Kiev.
Okay. and then they they withdrew from
there. So some decision was made at some
level uh to withdraw and and not take
Kiev immediately.
And ever since the the Russians have
been fighting the slow war, you've had
multiple seasons of of Rasputita that
have come and gone and right now also
it's not Rasputa which is the mud
season. Right now it is it is summer
summertime which means the ground is
hard. So they can make a move if they
want but they are choosing not to. So
then the question arises, why have the
Russians adopted this slow war strategy,
a frozen conflict approach? Why will
that not deplete their ammunition
stockpiles? Will it not deplete their
weapons stockpiles? Well, no, it won't.
Ever since the war started, the Russia
activated Russia activated its uh
industrial base and Russia now the
Russia's industrial base is now churning
out weapons after weapons, huge
quantities of weapons and arms and
ammunition and whatnot. They have huge
stockpiles and the stockpiles are
increasing in size and I've seen some
western assessments which say that
Russia is in very capable of sustaining
the war effort based on the current
stockpiles until 26 or 27.
And obviously they're going to produce
more they're going to stock they're
going to produce more weapons and what
not. So then the question of so Russia
so this continuous slow war is not
decreasing the stock piles it's
increasing the stock piles of Russia
because Russia has consciously
consciously decided to ramp up the
production of of weapons. So Russia is
fine. Russia is in in a great position.
So the question is then then the
question is what on earth is Russia
doing? Why the slow war strategy whilst
while while bolstering your stockpiles
and all that? It's because of the NATO
threat. So, Russia seems to have decided
that we will not take over Ukraine
because that will probably bring us
directly into conflict with NATO. Once
we take over Ukraine, we are on the
border with NATO nations. Ukraine
borders certain NATO nations. Okay,
Poland is an example.
Uh so if you take over Ukraine, you are
straight away borderto border with NATO
nations which which significantly
escalates chances of conflict and
miscalculation. So let's not do that.
Let this war go on. Let NATO get bogged
down in this. Uh they don't have
supplies. They don't have the mil the
industrial uh base in Europe. The
Americans are having to send their
supplies. Let them deplete everything.
And we also don't want to show all our
capabilities to NATO. We don't want to
throw our air force into the mix. Let it
go on as long as it needs to. Let NATO
get bogged down. Let the US get bogged
down. Um if they want to fight till the
last Ukrainian, let them fight till the
last Ukrainian exists. That's what they
are doing. Russia is also worried about
a confrontation with NATO and it wants
to be as prepared as possible in case
that scenario happens. So don't fight u
NATO directly. Let the war go on as long
as it needs to go on doesn't matter.
Keep on stockpiling you know ramping up
the production of your weapons stock
create huge stockpiles of whatever is
needed especially missiles and
everything else that's needed and in the
future if there's a war with NATO we are
well prepared. That is the Russian u
thinking as far as I can see.
Okay. Anikit says, "Is it safe to export
our best defense technologies like
Brahmos to countries like Indonesia and
Malaysia because they are highly
compromised nations by China? Plus,
these are Muslim countries." And there's
a news report that says India offered
longrange missile to Greece. Gree
Greece. Greece. What's Greece? Greece.
Greece which is a NATO country. Okay. Uh
first of all, let's not look at
everything from a religious perspective.
Uh I'm not sure about Malaysia but
Indonesia and India have great relations
um despite whatever religious angle may
exist. Okay. Let's not look at
everything from a religious perspective.
Let's not do that. Now when it comes to
exporting our defense equipment and
technology technologies to other
countries uh you typically don't export
the full version. You export what's
called an export version. So when it
comes to for example the US, let's say
they want to sell you the F-16, they
will sell you an export version which is
a dumbed down version of what they use.
If they sell you, if they offer you the
F-35, they will offer you a F-35 that is
at least 50% less capable than what the
one they use.
If the Chinese sell the J whatever to
Pakistan, they will sell a stupid
version of the J something to Pakistan.
they will not sell the full version of
the J whatever fighter plane to Pakistan
and so on. So you never sell the full
technology to another country. You
ensure that certain things are left out.
Okay?
It it it still may be a great weapon but
you don't sell the full capabilities.
You you keep something out. That's what
you do. It's it's it's standard
practice. It's called an export version
of the system.
So if you are selling the bramos to so
and so country, it will be an export
version of the bramos. I I'll leave it
at that and you will not sell it to
countries that in any way are are going
to be compromised in some way against
you. So if we have sold it to the
Philippines, let's say, we have thought
very carefully about it. We have thought
about every single possibility,
potential uh pitfall, every angle and
then we sold it to the Philippines, to
Vietnam, to whoever. um um in the in the
future to whoever else you have to you
have to do your due diligence very well
that let's say I sell this weapon system
even an export version to so and so
country will it fall in the wrong hands
will they send it to China or the US
right and will these nations then get
get a deeper understanding of our
secrets our secret the secrets of our
technologies you have to think about it
very carefully and you have to have
safeguards even when it comes to export
versions of of the of the technologies.
So for example, the Americans have F-16s
in Pakistan, but they have technicians
in Pakistan who never let the F-16s out
of their sight. Okay? So that's how they
ensure that it's not used for uh that
that nothing happens to the to the to
the weapon system. That's what they do.
I I have heard a rumor that India has uh
offered Greece with um a long range
missile which is fine. Greece is a NATO
country. Now why Greece is indeed a NATO
nation
but it's also a nation that is
threatened by another NATO nation. Do
you understand? Okay, we haven't opened
the map yet. It's been 1 hour. Well, let
me open the map and show you what the
deal is.
See, let's go to Greece. I will not walk
you through it. Let's straight go to
Greece. Here is Greece. It's a nation
with a whole bunch of islands all the
way everywhere. And to the east of
Greece, it is you have it its mortal
enemy, Turkey. Turkey. Turkey.
So
Turkey sits on Greek territory. Turkey
occupies Greek territory. Historical
Greek territory. Uh a thousand years
ago, everything that is Turkey today
used to be Greek.
This was all historically Greek
territory and Turkey threatens Greece
even now they would like to destroy
Greece and they keep threatening Greece
that in the middle of the night will be
you know we'll walk into your country so
Greece is threatened by Turkey its
number one threat its existential threat
is Turkey and both are NATO nations and
the US seems to be okay with the
situation so Greece obviously has to
look for other allies so we had an
alliance with Greece 2,300 something
years ago and we have we seem to be uh
kind of renewing that.
Uh so obviously we will have some kind
of proper due diligence that is done
when it comes to Greece that if if in
case we sell so and so weapons system
will it end up in American hands or
somewhere else we have to think about
that very clearly and uh once we are
clear about what will or will not happen
we can go ahead and make the actual
offer. So you can rest assured that
first of all we will not sell the full
version we'll sell an export version
which will still be good enough and
secondly we will do our due diligence
before selling a weapon system to
anybody and then there's a failsafe
thing that even if for whatever reason
it it ends up in Chinese hands or
American hands or whoever hands you they
will not get the entire full
understanding of our technology. Uh so
all all that will be there.
Yeah.
Okay. Mudra Makuana says, "Thanks for
all the free knowledge." Well, you're
very welcome. Uh, do you think putting
all the
do you think putting all the
geopolitical analysis and forecasting in
public on public forums uh like like
what I do here, could that potentially
that that forecasting and all that
information that I put out, could it
potentially be seen by our rivals and
enemies? And what's the probability of
them actually getting ideas from the
analysis?
That's a very good question you ask. So
I I do this very detailed forecasting,
don't I? On my geost strategy series and
I look at what's happened the past week
or so, the let's say the 10 most
important developments. Then I look at
soft signals. Then I I I
also then do some forecasting. I mean
the most important forecasts for the
next 3 months or 6 months or whatever
and those are pretty in-depth forecasts.
I look at multiple scenarios. I give
probability percentages and
I give historical precedents. It's
pretty detailed anal analysis isn't it?
Isn't it? The question is is that
information
too sensitive to put out in the public
domain? May is it possible that our
enemies
will see that and get ideas from it.
So we just took a question about
exporting weapons right
Brahmos
other missiles and so on to other other
countries and I said that you never
export the full version you export a
stripped down dumbed down version called
an export version right you don't give
the whole thing you give a version a
slightly lower version for export
similarly the analysis that I
and uh the scenarios I put out. Do you
think it's the full analysis and the
full detailed scenarios? No, it's an
it's an export version.
It's an export version that I put out in
the public domain.
The real thing is is not put out in
public. And what I put out in public I
is it's very clear from my perspective
that you know if you if you are a
government if you are in government if
you're in charge of geopolitical
forecasting and strategic analysis in
government then then it's not difficult
for you to come up with the same
scenarios.
So I don't put out anything that's
sensitive.
I don't put out anything that's really
like
yeah sensitive. Essentially I I the
analysis I put out out there in the
public domain are export versions of the
analysis. They're not really stupid or
dumbed down versions but simplified
versions. For example, I generally put
out three scenarios. One with
probability around 70 to 80% sometimes
90%, one with a 30-ish% probability and
one with a 5 10% probability. Right? But
generally you have multiple scenarios
like you can have five six scenarios for
something. I usually put out three
sometimes four but you can have seven
eight scenarios and you have to take all
of them scenar them very seriously and
you can do very detailed analysis about
each scenario you can g do game
theoretic analysis for each scenario you
can do network analysis you can do so
much more I don't put any of that out do
I so uh rest assured I'm not putting out
any sensitive information in the public
domain analysis is well it's it's at
best an academic exercise that what I'm
doing what I'm putting out um the real
analysis is is that I do it is super
super sensitive and very very highly
valuable. It would cost you millions of
dollars if you were to purchase it
possibly. I'm just saying. Okay.
Okay.
Uh Prrenai Paul says, "Are there any
signals um you can spot that indicate
that Operation Synindu Round two could
happen soon. Apart from Pakistan doing
something stupid again, what else
hypothetically could trigger the next
phase in your assessment?
Uh what could trigger next phase of
operation Synindhur? Look once again
um
export version right. So look
what could trigger operation zindur a
Pakistani terror attack somewhere
uh or or continuous Pakistani attempts
to infiltrate terrorists into India
across the LOC or the international
border or whatever. Um beyond that I
don't see what could trigger uh
operation synindur round two. Um we have
made it very clear our doctrine is is
completely different now. Any terror
attack in India will be regarded as an
act of war by Pakistan.
So that only is what I see as something
that could potentially trigger operation
zindur part 2. either a terror attack
somewhere in India a proper like one
hopes it never happens but you know a
large scale terror attack like what
happened what happened in Pahelgam
that's an example of uh of something
that could trigger uh round two of
operation Sindur or Pakistani attempts
to continuously attempt to infiltrate
terrorists across the border or LOC
these two things could trigger operation
Zindur some version of it part
Beyond that, I'm not really sure what.
Could I think of something else right
now? I can't. So,
Inferno says, um,
where China, um, where China has failed
to make a profitable
investment with Pakistan, Trump is going
into business with Pakistan. Is this
wishful thinking? Does this question
Trump's credibility as a businessman? It
does not Trump uh, it does not question
Mr. Trump's credibility as a
businessman. He is uh his objective is
to make massive profits. Um so his see
his objective is different from that of
China. China's investment in Pakistan
was a strategic investment.
Okay. Trump's investment is a
is exploitative.
It's different. They have different
objectives.
China's investment in Pakistan was the
China Pakistan economic uh corridor CPEC
right it was the Pakistani leg of the
chi Chinese barri belt and road
initiative one
belt and road initiative right one road
to rule them all one belt to bind them
that sort of thing so the CPC was the
Pakistani branch of that and the
objective from China's perspective was
to create infrastructure in Pakistan
that would uh bolster Chinese uh that
that would uh
that would be strategically sound and
and profitable for China not from the
money perspective but from an
infrastructure perspective. So ports,
roads and so on and that would give
China more inroads in the region and
also chi give China warm water ports in
the western Indian Ocean, the so-called
Arabian Sea and and so on. That's what
China intended. The entire belt and road
initiative is an infrastructure building
initiative
and that's what they're doing in
Pakistan through the CPC and it doesn't
hasn't really worked out for a variety
of reasons but uh so that's what has
happened with visavi China's China has
pushed in has has sunk a lot of money
into Pakistan for building
infrastructure for their own for their
own benefit infrastructure. Now Trump is
not building infrastructure in Pakistan.
Trump has no no interest in building
infrastructure in Pakistan. Trump wants
to exploit Pakistan's national natural
resources. What natural resources? Oil
and gas most likely in Baluchasthan etc.
and also rare earth uh minerals rare
earth elements.
So cumulatively if you take all the oil
and gas that Pakistan has to offer plus
whatever rare earths and so on and other
things Pakistan has to offer plus if you
add in the cryptocurrency scene and all
that these are things that Trump is
investing in then it the total amount
speculatively fig whatever is said to be
in the in the in the realm of about $50
trillion. You know the untapped
resources that you have all of that put
together. So Trump wants to exploit
that. He wants to set up companies in
Pakist set up operations in Pakistan
that will drill and pull out the oil and
gas and enrich him and also rare earths
and enrich Trump. So China is not
seeking to enrich person X or person Y.
They want to build infrastructure
that will
help them advance
their hegemony, you know, eventual
hedgemony over the world.
Trump has no such interest. He's not
trying to advance American interests
over here. He is trying to enrich
himself. It's a personal thing for him.
He is the president of the US, but he is
at the same time enriching himself.
Amass trying to amass wealth and extract
wealth out of nations like Pakistan.
Now, India has way more to offer in
terms of natural resources. But India is
not up for sale. Pakistan is up for
sale. That's why Trump is so interested
in Pakistan. So it's a from from his
perspective, it's a sound investment. It
may actually end up paying a paying
dividends for him. So it does not bring
into question Trump's credibility as a
business person. It does not.
Krishna Krishna of the of the Surinabis
Netherlands says, "What's the connection
between the Korgan hypothesis and the
Arian invasion/migration/
whatever else theory?" Good question. uh
the kuran hypothesis
uh it was propounded by Maria Gimbotas
or what that's the name I suppose of the
person and what does the kuran
hypothesis say it says that uh see in in
Eurasia there's this region called the
pontic caspian step
and the kuran hypothesis says that
beginning around 4,000 BC or no not
4,000 BC 4,000 years before today around
that time there was an expansion of the
Korgan people the Kuran culture out of
the Pontic Caspian step and this
expansion of the these culture and the
people associated with it it accounts
for the spread of the Indo-Uropean
languages worldwide across Eurasia
that's the Kuran hypothesis now let's
address the question of what is the
spontic caspian step uh let us quickly
take take a look at Google and we'll
search for
on tick caspian
step. What is this thing? I will not go
to the Wikipedia image this time page
this time. Uh okay here. Oh I suppose we
should then. Okay as always please
remember that Wikipedia is not a
reliable source of information but we
will just for the sake of uh brevity
we'll look into this. This colored
region the purple light purple region is
the Pontic Caspian step. You can see
much of that is the north Caucasus
region and it covers part of Ukraine
part of central Asia as well. Okay. Um
it's it's uh between the Black Sea and
the Caspian Sea and north of that that
region is called the Pontic Caspian step
or the Pontic step or whatever you want
to call it. So according to the kuran
hypothesis
the this culture spread out from this
region and expanded in all directions
and that accounts for the spread of the
Indo-Uropean languages
and that also is the originator of the
so-called Arian invasion of India. Now
if you want to ask ask what is the Kuran
culture they had these mounts burial
mounts called korgans.
Korgans what are korgans? Let's take a
look at a kan.
So I don't know which which language is
it Russian? Is it something Turkish? But
these mounds, these big burial mounds in
which royalty was buried or aristocracy
was buried. These mounds were called
kuras. So this culture that was based
out of this region, they had this
practice, this tradition of of burying
their their prominent people in these
mounds called gorgans.
So that's the Gorgan hypothesis that the
people who have this tradition of
burying in Gorgans, they spread out of
the pontic kaspin step about 4,000 years
ago, four 4 and a half thousand years
ago or whatever it is and they were the
the the original people who spoke and
maybe a protoindo-uropean language and
from there it all spread spread out and
maybe people like me we are descendants
of those invaders people like me evil
north Indians evil aran invaders right
people like me so That's the the
connection between the Korggan
hypothesis and the Arian migration
invasion theory. The question is I would
like to once again raise this question.
What proof do you have that these people
spoke in Induropean language? And what
proof do you have that this spread the
spread of this culture and these people
uh led to the spread of the Indo-Uropean
languages? Have you found an example of
of an inscription in an indo
indo-uropean language associated with
the Kuran culture? just one give me one
example there's no such thing so they
are pulling these ideas out of well thin
air I suppose
right Shri Ramachandra Maha says how
will India counter the ctographic
distortion of Indian maps so
Indians are a very emotional people and
anytime you have somebody putting up a
map of some part of the world for
example our Israeli friends they love
putting out maps and they make it a
point to put out maps that of India maps
of the world or the region in which
India is depicted as being without
Kashmir and without Arunach Pradesh.
Israel has this long-standing tendency
of doing this. I once took the trouble
to point this out of pointing this out
to the Israeli uh ambassador and he
actually had the map pulled down and he
apologized. But then it start it
continues. So the point is
what do you do about this?
Well, my dear friends,
the only way to counter any ctographic
distortion of maps is by putting facts
on the ground.
The fact is that
P is under Pakistani occupation.
Then why will the rest of the world not
show it as part of Pakistan? Tell me why
Akai Chin is under Chinese occupation.
Then why will the west will the rest of
the world not show it as part of China?
The only way to counter all these
is by putting facts by changing the
facts on the ground. Until that happens,
let's not complain and cry and moan
about things. It is what it is. These
territories deal with it are not under
our control. They're not. But we insist
that we should show the maps in a
certain way. And we are right to insist
that because these territories were
taken illegally from us. But the fact is
that they are not with us right now. So
the only way to counter all of this is
to change the facts on the ground.
That's it. And I think it's it's time we
we start showing
putting up maps showing Tibet as a
disputed territory. It's high time we do
that.
Okay. Vashisha says India declared a
critical mineral mission in the August
of 2024 but we still face problems in 25
China mineral sanctions that's right
what does it represent we just take
decisions but we don't take action or
time was too short for results it seems
Indian government potential threat
could not take effective measures okay
first of all let's take a look at what
is this uh critical mineral mission I
think it's called the national critical
minerals mission if I'm not mistaken let
me Just see if I am right. Critical
minerals
mission.
Yes, National Critical Mineral Mission.
That's right. So, yes, my memory does
serve me right. Now, let's take a look
at this uh uh this overview. The
National Critical Minerals Mission is a
flagship initiative launched by the
Indian government to ensure a secure and
sustainable supply of critical minerals
for India's etc etc etc. The mission
aims to establish a robust framework for
self-reliance blah blah blah encouraging
domestic exploration, mining,
processing, recycling as well as
facilitating Indian partners,
international partnerships. Uh what are
the specifics of all this? Strengthening
all stages of critical minerals value
chain exploration etc etc. Encourages
Indian companies to acquire assets
abroad. Uh key initiatives exploration
geological survey of India is
undertaking ext
these are the action levels. The
Geological Survey of India is
undertaking extensive exploration
projects to identify and assess critical
mineral resources. Well, that's
something that is happening. We have
identified a list of 30 critical
minerals uh with 24 including some some
schedule or something. Uh we know what
these things are blah blah blah. So the
only action I'm saying right now is that
the geological survey of India is
undertaking extensive exploration
projects to identify and assess the
critical mineral resources that we have.
So action is being taken. We are in the
initial phase of the national critical
mineral mission. I mean if we had
started this in 2014 for example, we
would be in a very different position
today. But you know what? Better late
than never. We have woken up 10 years
into the Modi government, right? 2024.
So it's in 2024 that the government woke
up. Oh wow, these minerals are critical.
If we rely on others for these minerals,
then they may deprive of us of these
things and we may be in big trouble. So
let's make a list of the critical
minerals. So we have now identified 30
critical minerals. Now we have told the
geo geological survey of India go out
there spread out and uh undertake
extensive projects exploration projects
to identify what reserves we have what
resources we have and assess the
quantities and all that. So that's
what's happening right now. So this is
the initial phase of this uh mission.
Once we identify where we have minerals
and what reser resources we have, what
reserves we have, then we'll start start
maybe
exploiting them uh digging them up,
pulling them out of the ground. That's
one thing you do. Then you have to
purify it, clean it up and make it um
transform it into something that can be
used by industry that's another thing.
So maybe this this whole process takes
10 years. So we started this mission in
August 24. It's been less than a year
and now we are facing problems because
of China.
So in India it looks like we wake up
only when there's a fire under our
backside right. So anyway I would like
to thank China for lighting the fire. So
at least in the next 10 years we'll
become hopefully self-sufficient. Uh I
would have love for loved for this to
happen 10 years ago. If it had happened
if this initiative had been taken 10
years ago by now we would have been most
likely to a large extent
self-sufficient.
But it is what it is. This is India
right? In India everything happens in
this manner unless there's a critical
emergency
no action is taken. So now that China
has two fifth generation fighter planes
now the government of India will wake up
and we will now now take things on
mission mode like they say mission mode.
It is the way it is. Okay. India is a
very complicated country huge
bureaucracy and whatn not and there are
lots of constraints but uh at least we
have the mission now and we are working
on it. So I suppose by 2035 we will be
self-sufficient. I hope so. Okay.
All right. Geopolitical Dubai says um
why doesn't Elon Musk want to
manufacture in India? Is it because of
Trump's pressure or the Chinese don't
want him to do so? Uh I don't think
that's a there's a Trump factor in this
because Elon Musk has been around from
before Trump before his fallout before
his divorce with Mr. Trump during Pride
Month.
Okay. So, I don't think there's a Trump
factor in this. He has been reluctant to
invest in India for a very long time.
What could be the reasons for it? He has
a giga factory or something in China.
He's got a big operation in China. And
of course, there's a China factor. The
Chinese will give him both the carrot
and the stick. They will give him
inducements. Then, you know what? We'll
allow you to set up more operations in
China. And you know how efficiently
things are in China. Why do you need to
go to India? And secondly, so that's the
inducement part that we will give you
more better stuff. You can you can have
more operations in China and you will
make more profits. Gone, isn't it? So
that's the inducement part. That's a
carrot part. Now the stick part also the
Chinese the Chinese will signal to Elon
Musk that look you have all these
investments in China. You have these
factories etc in China. But if you open
up something in India as well, well,
things will become difficult for you in
China and you will not be able to make
so many profit, so much profits and you
know how things are in India. Things
don't really work the way they work in
China and so on. So that's one reason
the China factor. Secondly, it's much
harder to do to start something in India
compared to doing compared to starting
it in China. Ease of doing business, red
tape, bureaucracy, hurdles,
so on. So because of these reasons Elon
Musk I suppose is uh has been reluctant
to manufacture in India and now I
suppose he's uh going to double down on
manufacturing in the US possibly let's
see so that's the reason in the way I
see it why Elon Musk has uh stayed away
from India
Shri Ramachandra Maha says the question
is what is the alternative to the
straight of hormones when it comes to
India's trade
So please understand this my friends. Uh
the straight of hormones is not
relevant to us from a trading
perspective. It has nothing to do with
our trade.
We don't use the straight of hormones
for trading.
It's vital for energy reasons. Let's go
to the map so that we understand what
the deal is.
Let's open up the map.
So first of all for those who may not be
aware where is the straight of Hormos
it's to the west the western sea of
Sarashtra and this is the straight of
Hormos okay which connects the Persian
Gulf with the Gulf of Oman and the Gulf
of Oman opens up into the Indian western
Indian Ocean okay so the straight of
Hormos is this choke point over here
uh and it's about I don't know 50-ish
kilometersish wide
64. It depends on what what how you
measure the thing.
Yeah. 56 here and so on. It's pretty
it's it's a pretty narrow choke point.
And why is it important for India? Why
is it important for the rest of the
world? Because a very significant
percentage of the world's energy in
terms of fossil fuels which is oil and
gas. it all of that flows out from the
Persian Gulf which is this region
through the straight of Hormos into the
Indian Ocean and from the Indian Ocean
it goes wherever else.
So as we know Iran, Iraq, Kuwait, Saudi
Arabia, UAE etc. are major major
producers of oil and exporters of oil
and all of that export comes through
super tankers and tankers which pass
through the straight of Hormuz
and about I don't know 40% 50% of our
energy the energy we use comes from the
Persian Gulf through the state of
Hormos. So that is the deal. That's why
the state of hormones is so important
for India. It has nothing to do with
trade. It has all to do with energy.
Energy, fossil fuels, oil and gas. So if
for whatever reason the state of Hormos
gets blockaded. Okay? Then the energy
stops flowing and the global oil prices
energy prices shoot up which means
everything the prices of everything
shoots up 50% 100% God knows what it
will lead to a global crisis. It will
lead to a glob global recession. If the
straight of hormones is blockaded for
any period of time, any reasonable any
any lengthy period of time. So that is
the deal with the straight of hormones.
It is all about energy. It has nothing
to do with uh trade and there is no
alternative to it. You see that's the
problem. I mean there's no immediate
alternative to it. If you want to bypass
the trade of Hormos then you have to
build pipelines.
Now how do you build pipelines from Iraq
through Saudi Arabia and so it's it's
monumental task which is why there's
essentially no alternative to the
straight of
anime Paul says while India's GDP is
growing much of the wealth seems
concentrated among the elite what are
the most effective measures we must take
to meaningfully raise GDP per capita to
improve the quality of life for the
average Indian
so the way to meaningfully okay so first
of all we have to address this uh what
is it elite elite this is a term the
west loves to use and our people read
the English-speaking media from the west
and we absorb these terms subconsciously
elite India's elite are evil because
they have all the wealth and they are
depriving the poor Indians from wealth
see I'll tell you what happened what
what the deal is
um in India there's a lack of
opportunity
right for progress for for the common
person lack of opportunities. The only
opportunities in India exist in the big
cities, metropolitan cities. If you are
in it, you have to go to Bangaluru. You
have to go to Hyderabad,
right? If you are in the finance sector,
you have to go to Mumbai. If you are in
some other sectors, you have to go to
Ahmedabad or Delhi or Chennai
or is there any other big city that you
can think of? I suppose Kolkata right
and so on. It's only a number of cities
where all the opportunities exist. So if
you are a young person with big dreams
and all and you want to do something big
in life, you have no choice but to
migrate to one of these cities and start
from scratch
and the people who are left behind in
the other cities other parts of India
they don't get opportunities of becoming
wealthy unless they well very few
opportunities. So the people who live in
the big cities,
even all of those people, let's say you
have 20 million people in city X, I
assure you those 20 million are not
super rich. It's only the 1% of the 1%
who really know how to make money and
who will become rich. But imagine that
we have the same opportunities that you
have in the big cities all across India.
Well, then you will have so many more
people who become rich in India because
there are lots of intelligent, capable
people who for whatever reason are not
able to come to a big city. So the the
problem is that
the opportunities are not being created
by the states by many of the states. I
will not name any state but so many
states don't create the opportunities.
Why aren't there 10 tire one cities in
each state of India? I don't understand
why.
Right. And that's that's a problem
that's always been around. I remember
during 2014 during the 2014 general
election campaign, Prime Minister Modi
had said uh he was then the candidate
for being the prime minister. He was
still the chief minister of Gujarat at
the time. He had said why don't we make
a 100 new cities across India where you
have all the opportunities that you get
in a big city and the cities will be
built from scratch welld designed with
all the amenities all the facilities
that you have in any any worldass city
create a 100 cities like this all across
India and then see how India India's
economy takes off it was a fantastic
idea but once he becomes prime minister
he realizes that this is you know it's
easier to say this than do it there's a
whole governance machinery that will
come and stand in your way
and states will not be willing in in in
some cases maybe many cases to do such
things.
Then what do you do? So then that became
the smart cities thing. Then you will
we'll take 100 existing cities and turn
them into smart cities and then I don't
know what happened to it. That's how
dreams die in India because the system
doesn't want things to change.
The system wants things to stay the
same. It will it will take a monumental
superhuman leader to change things in
India.
So what needs to be done? What needs to
be done is very simple. Every state
should create 10 tire one cities. Take
10 towns and transform them into tier
one cities with all the facilities with
all the opportunities that will in
attract investors and attract the best
talent from within the state. then the
whole country will flower and bloom with
opportunity.
But no, we we don't want that in India,
right? So who's stopping us? It is our
system that's stopping us. It's not the
Indian people who are stopping India
from developing. The Indian people are
are trapped. They're victims. It's the
system that prevents India from taking
off. India can take off like anything.
You have no idea how much potential
there is in India. There's no country
with the potential that India has. But
so so I I gave you the solution. That's
the solution. Every state must make the
decision. Within 5 years we will have
five we'll have 10 tire one cities in
our state. We'll do whatever it takes.
We'll do whatever it takes. We we'll ask
the state central government for for
money to do this. Whatever it takes.
There is enough money in India. Imagine
forget about five years. Imagine in 10
years each state has 10 world-class
cities with all the opportunities that
you need. Then you will no longer have
this divide of wealth and elites and all
that nonsense. Everybody will get
opportunities. So once in in let's say
in 10 years you have 10 cities like this
then you in the next 10 years you extend
the same facilities and you extend the
same development and opportunities to
tire two cities. Take two take 10 tire
to citizen each state and you give the
same thing to them then in 10 10 20 30
years the whole country is transformed
there's no none of this nonsense of you
know uh inequality and all that nonsense
it's it's possible but it it will not
work in the current system you need a
different kind of system in India for
this to happen
all right I've given you the solution
okay uh fit boy
fit boys I
um well thank you so much I'm sorry
namaste and thank you so much for
raising my standards yeah well you
you're very welcome very welcome does
India come under western sphere of
influence yes it does yes it does what
language am I speaking which what what
language am I comfortable in what kind
of clothes am I wearing
and so on all these books behind me what
language are they written in all these
books behind me all these books here all
the books over here which you can't see
all the books in my other rooms what
language are they written this written
written in English. Uh if you want to if
you want to uh go for a job interview,
what language do you need to speak? If
you speak with a very Indian accent,
will you get a good job in India? You
will not get a good job in India if you
speak like this. You have to speak in a
very sophisticated manner in a very
foreign manner to get a job. And if you
can just speak English with a certain
extent h accent half 70% of your job is
done of getting a job offer and so on.
Our constitution the so-called democracy
that we have the calendar the way our
society is structured everything is
western western in nature. Yes we are we
are completely colonized even now.
So yes India does come under the western
sphere of influence. It does it's just a
fact. Just a fact in case people don't
don't see it. I mean when you are in the
forest you don't see the forest because
only the only thing you see is trees
right? Where is the forest? Where's the
forest? I only see trees. That's the
situation for most Indians. So deeply
conditioned they don't see the real
situation.
Uh Dhanush has a very long question. How
do we address the problem of severe
Indian inferiority complex? I knew it
was there but never knew the scale of it
until I was speaking with my dad. He was
strongly claiming that India lost the
recent conflict with Pakistan because
the western media said that India did
not win because the western media did
not say that India won and no amount of
evidence and convincing could change
him. It was so frustrating to see him
defend his point of view. It's a clear
case and this is very concerning because
when the nation does good, foreign
influence can reduce our morale and this
should be addressed. I think younger
generations are doing a little better.
But we need to do something to change
the older generations. Uh
I I I I can I I commiserate with you. I
can sense your frustration when others
are are they are showing this this
attitude. You don't care. But when your
own relatives, your own parents, you see
it there. Well, it's very frustrating.
Of course, I understand. Uh the question
is what do we need to do? What's the
question? How do we address this problem
of severe inferiority complex? See, I'll
tell you a very straightfor I'll be very
blunt with you. There's nothing you can
do that will change the mindset of your
of the older people. Once
most people once they reach a certain
age, they can't change. I think that age
is around 40 years. Once you reach
around 40 years, the average person is
incapable of changing whatever they've
learned and absorbed in the first 40
years of of their life. That is going to
determine their attitude and approach
towards everything going forward. And
nothing you do, no matter how you how
much you convince, no matter how much
evidence and everything you put in front
of them, won't make a difference to
them. They have already decided what
they've decided and that's it. So my po
what I would say very bluntly to you is
don't waste your time trying to change
somebody's mind. Even if it's your dad,
it is what it is. So then then the
question is how do we address this
problem of the severe Indian inferiority
complex
regular viewers of my channel will know
what I'll say? We have to change the
education system.
The education system, what does it tell
us? West is best. Foreign languages are
better than Indian languages. See, you
don't even have to say west is best.
When you say that English is a superior
language to your mother tongue because
you cannot speak your mother tongue
tongue in school. You can only speak
English and the better you speak English
the better you are. That itself
incul you know it it it it um indirectly
creates a sense of inferiority in your
mind because then you start associating
everything that associated with English
as superior. So when somebody from the
BBC with their British accent says that
India was unable to win, you're going to
believe that person despite whatever
other data may be in front of you
because this inferiority complex has
been has been drilled into you since the
time you were 3 years old. Right? So the
education system has to be changed. The
language of instruction has to be
changed. It has to be the mother tongue
and the civilizational language should
be Hindi. English should be um should be
made not compulsory. If someone wants to
learn English, it's their it's their
personal problem and personal choice.
But English should not be uh taught in
schools. Go to Thailand. Go to Japan. Do
they teach English?
They don't teach English. Go to China.
Do they teach English in school? Go to
Germany. Go to France. Do they speak Do
they teach English? No. Quantum
mechanics. the theory without which this
communication would not happen. What
language was quantum mechanics developed
in? It was developed in German and
French not in English and so on. So I
can give you so many examples. My point
is you have to change all of these
things. The only way you will we will
address the problem of the severe Indian
infinity complex is by drastically
totally overholding and reforming the
education system. Someday hopefully it
happens. It's not happening anytime
soon.
Okay, I have come to the end of the
questions that I selected. had selected
20 questions. Those are done. Let's see
if we have some uh maybe I can take some
questions from the live chat for a bit.
For a bit best books to study
geopolitics, please inform. There are no
books for geopolitics.
You can't study geopolitics from books.
I read three books from geopolitics each
500 pages long and that's it. Now I know
what geopolitics is. It doesn't work
like that. There are no textbooks on
geopolitics. Go to your favorite online
retailer, Amazon, Flipkart, whatever it
is, and go to the book section, search
for geopolitics. You won't find a
textbook on geopolitics. You won't find
that, right? There isn't any. Maybe I
have to write one.
So, there are no books for studying
geopolitics. How do I understand
geopolitics? Because I've spent my
entire life studying history.
My primary focus was science, obviously,
physics, mathematics. But in my free
time, I would read more because I'm a
goddamn nerd, right? So, I would read
more when I would get like two hours a
day for maybe doing some sports. I loved
sports of course but apart from that I
would do I would read so I read a lot of
world history lot of world history and
that's how I I because this the patterns
and regularities that you observe in
world history they are being played out
today in the form of geopolitics today's
history um
what is history today for us used to be
geopolitics back in the day okay let's
take maybe a few more questions uh
Um let's see what questions do we have.
Anonymous scientist says why did Richard
Nixon hate India and Indians? Why was
JFK pro India? Let's take Nixon first.
The Pakistanis helped him a lot. Nixon
was very interested in in in China in
having a mo they taunted with China and
Pakistan served as a mediator for that.
So Pakistan was very useful for for the
US and India was very intrigent and
India's prime minister for the longest
time was was Mr. Neu who had this habit
of lecturing the world from a position
of great moral superiority when he was
not from the rest of the world's
perspective perhaps that morally
superior and so on. So it's a very
annoying attitude to have and approach
to have for the rest of the world. So
maybe that's one of the reasons why uh
Nixon and and his best pal Kissinger did
not have any great affection or love or
regard for India. That's one of the
reasons JFK was pro India. JFK was um it
was in the beginning of the of the cold
war a time when India had not really
made it stand very clearly and maybe at
the time the US felt and JFK felt that
you know there's still a chance that
maybe we can have India on our side
that's why he made various offers to
India offers of a permanent uh uh seat
on the UN security council I think the
Americans did it before JFK of course
but uh the JFK offered India uh nuclear
weapons technology which India revolved
and so on So
all right um
let's take some more questions.
Uh Sri Ramachandra Anamaha says what are
the benefits of of experimenting in
microgravity. So let's say you want to
send uh human beings to Mars. Uh it
takes about 8 n 10 months to reach Mars
which is a long period of time. Uh and
let's say you have to for example in the
future someday send a mission of
astronauts to the asteroid belt maybe to
extract minerals from the asteroids
asteroid u um what do they call it
uh asteroid exploitation farming
whatever it is um resource extraction.
So you have to keep the human body under
in essentially zero gravity for months
or years at a time. So we have to
understand what the effects of that are
on the human body and on various
substances.
For example, you want to carry food food
materials maybe plants or whatever into
space and keep that u in in in
microgravity for for years at a time.
What's going to be the effect of that?
So what we doing is we we're planning
for the long term. In the future we want
to have long space missions. Maybe we'll
send a mission to let's say Europa.
Let's say we may send a mission to
Jupiter for example,
do a few orbits of Jupiter and come
back. Whatever you can imagine. So that
these missions take years and you're
going to be in microgravity for the
longest time. So what's the effect of
that in the human body? What's the
effect of that on your materials? What's
the effect of that on your food stuffs?
Um and so on. So that's why you want to
experiment under controlled conditions.
uh so that you know what will happen
when conditions are not that much under
under your control. So that's why you
place uh astronauts you put astronauts
in orbit maybe in in the international
space station or whatever keep them for
6 months keep them for one year. The
Russians the Soviets had the the longest
records which probably still stand of uh
humans in orbit. So then you get to see
what what are the effects of that on on
people. So that's why we do it. That's
the that's the benefit so that we
understand how the human body behaves
and performs and what are the stresses
that the human go body um is is faced
with uh under such circumstances and
situations. That's why we do it.
Uh
um
okay. Let's see what else. We got a lot
of questions here. We'll take a few more
for today.
Uh, Nutan Roshan says, "Recent Matura
Batpuri ASI site shows shows
civilizational continuity for 3,500 to
1,000 BC with some young. What are my
views on it? Will it show AMT as Arian
just a joke theory?
So, it simply bolsters what we already
know. It it corroborates what we already
know. Um we know that see when it comes
to the uh so-called Harapan phase of our
history harapan phase industal phase
phase of our history we have cultural
continuity that goes back 9 and a half
thousand years the same cultural
elements you see today you see those
cultural elements even 9,000 years ago
so the this what you are telling me over
here I've not seen it yet this p piece
of news but once again it shows the same
thing that our culture is continuous us
our culture hasn't had a discontinuity
somewhere.
If there was an Arian invasion or
migration, you would see a discontinuity
in culture that before this migration
happened, you had one kind of culture
and then suddenly you see a new kind of
culture in the archae archaeological
record. But that's not the case. You see
the same culture all the way to 9,500
years before today, even even before
that, I suppose. So yeah, no surprise. I
haven't seen this piece of news, but
there's no surprise. And this
corroborates what I have been saying and
what many other people uh historians
like BBR and so on have been saying for
the longest time. So fantastic. I will
check it out. Thank you for bringing
this. Thank you for the for your
attention to this matter.
I'll pay attention to it. Um
okay. Mavin says, "Why didn't Biden stop
India from buying Russian oil and
selling to Europe? It was obvious that
it would help India. Biden regime seems
better than Trump." Well, if you Yeah,
that's that's that's a point I've made a
few times, including in probably the
Indian interest, one of the recent
episodes. If you look at the Biden
regime's attitude and approach towards
India and the Trump regime's attitude
and approach towards India since January
this year, it's very different. Overall,
Biden the Biden regime's approach
towards India was kind of better for
India than what the Trump's approach
what Trump's approach has been. Of
course, Biden started the Biden regime.
It's so the beginning of project K
cookie land for Christ the Manipur
crisis which was all which is all
mediated by external forces right there
is that uh but beyond that
be beyond that one thing and the attempt
to interfere in India's elections beyond
that u like you say Biden did not stop
India from buying Russian oil um and
even Trump thus far hasn't stopped it
but I they are now making very big
threats.
So Trump
uh right now there's some some kind of
bill in the US uh Congress I believe
that could potentially impose 500%
tariffs on India because we are buying
Russian oil. So that's a very different
approach. Why didn't Biden stop India?
Um because look they wanted India's
cooperation on a multiple on on a
multiplicity of issues especially when
it comes to China and they knew that if
India buys oil from Russia it's not
going to be a national security threat
for the US. So they tolerated it as long
as India cooperated on other things.
That's the kind of tradeoff there was.
So they wanted India's cooperation when
it comes to China when it comes to the
Indopacific region when it comes to the
Quad and various other things. as long
as you we were we were willing to give
us give them that they were I suppose
willing to look the other way when we
were buying uh Russian oil and not
participating in US sanctions but Trump
seems to have a maximalist approach
which uh I think is not going to go very
well for us go very well with us it's
going to create more rifts between India
and the US
um
okay let's Uh
yeah, I'm not aware of Kilad, so I won't
answer that question because
I have already addressed the F-35
question. What is this S IIA? Why are
Indians not allowed in by some South
Koreans and Israelis? Restaurants which
are in India. Is the government aware of
that? The owners are Korean and Israeli
and these restaurants are in India, but
Indians are not allowed there. Well,
that's unacceptable. I am not aware of
this. If it is the the case, then this
should be looked into very seriously and
strict action should be taken.
If this is the if this is indeed true.
So, South Korean restaurant owners who
have restaurants in India are not
allowing Indians inside. Really?
And Israeli restaurant owners whose
restaurants are in India are not
allowing Indians in those Israeli
restaurants in India. Well, that's
unacceptable if that is true. So I don't
know if why it is so but unacceptable if
it is true.
Okay.
Separ Krishna Giri says is India
planning for a space station? India has
a plan for a space station sometime in
the 2030s.
The first step is to put human beings in
space in into earth orbit low earth
orbit. So there's the Gagyan project. I
don't know when it starts. We haven't
even done the test flight yet. Unmanned
test flight. I suppose we would have we
should have at least a couple of
unmanned test flights. We've had some
issues with the rockets recently. So I
think uh I'm not sure what's going on.
Uh ever since SpaceX became a big thing,
ISRO has gone to sleep. I'm not blaming
the ISRO engineers and scientists and
leadership for this. It's the
government,
right? Because see Space X has reusable
rockets which means their their cost is
very less. Cost per kilo is very less.
Now for launching something into space
it's much less than what ISRO can quote.
So ISRO for the longest time had this
USB unique selling point that we are the
cheapest launch provider in the world.
Our launches are the cheapest. If you
have 10 kilos it will cost only this
much. Others are charging that much.
NASA will charge you that much but we
are only charging this much. But now
SpaceX has come and they're charging
that much only now because their
technology is so efficient.
So now ISRO when was the last time ISRO
launched a rock satellite for somebody
else outside of India. I'm not sure. So
ISRO seems to have gone into dormcancy
mode. I don't know how many launches
we're doing every year. Maybe four or
five. I I don't know. And if you do very
few launches then you're going to have
problems because you're not doing it
over and over again. So you may have
problems that creep up and then rockets
rocket launches fail after that and so
on. Uh so uh we we have plans on paper
for a space station. I don't know. I
don't think the government is really
taking space seriously right now at this
point in time. Maybe there are bigger
bigger things to worry about. But hey,
we have different departments and and
ministries, right? So you can work at
work work on several things at the same
time. Uh but yeah, that's where we are
right now.
Uh okay, maybe one or two questions
more.
Um
let us see let us see what do we have
anonymous scientist says is nuclear
fishision energy better than solar
energy how far are we from harnessing
fusion energy fusion we are very far
away I'm not sure uh look we have
various fusion projects outside of India
one is the Chinese artificial sun system
uh which I believe is a tokamak based
system to tokamak is to th toidal
machine in which you have plasma that is
kept at very high temperatures and it's
it's confined through magnetic
confinement that's that's called a
tokamak it's it's a Russian word the
tokamak was was invented by the by the
Soviets in the 20th century the Chinese
have taken that and that that concept
and they are working on that for fusion
I'm not sure if they have achieved
sufficient fusion yet or not but yeah
there's work in progress there are other
other such experiments also going on but
fusion is still in the future maybe 10
years in the future so possibly fish is
right here uh I'm not sure if it's
better than solar energy solar energy is
free so we can put up solar farms in
deserts and it can give you essentially
unlimitless amounts of energy uh but
that is constrained by weather and in in
in in uh in deserts you have dust and uh
sand that can cover the soil panels. So
that has to be addressed. Sometimes the
soil is is shifty. So that's another
problem because you want the panels to
be at a certain angle and maybe shift
their angle uh throughout the day
depending on the position of the sun and
so on so forth. Uh so there are there
are those constraints with solar energy
and fish energy is is like well super
clean as long as you do it properly and
as long as you have file material it's
it's limitless amounts of energy that
you can generate if you have sufficient
nuclear reactors. It's essentially just
steam engines at the end of the day. The
nuclear reactor gives you the heat which
then powers the steam engine. That's
essentially what nuclear fishision
energy is when it comes to electricity
generation. So these are all good
alternatives. uh fish energy is is very
clean and it's very reliable. Solar and
wind and thermal and hydro and all they
depend on external factors. Um so the
thing that you can rely on the best I
suppose is uh uh fish energy nuclear
energy but you would need large numbers
of reactors for that and why can't you
have it fusion there's still some time
to go for that maybe a decade perhaps
okay let's take one last question this
is the last question for the day spade
has asked this question what's your take
on Ilon creating America party when the
deep state allow it has he created that
he's been talking about that he's been
very upset with this big beautiful bill
of Mr. Trump. He's been uh criticizing
it for the for the longest time and
that's one of the reasons why he had
this has this that's why he's had this
fallout this breakup this divorce with
Mr. Trump um and he's been saying that
you know if this bill is passed he will
create this party America party or
something. Has he created it? I'm not
sure. I've not looked into it. I don't
look at news from an or perspective. So
I don't know if he creates it
maybe well it may be dangerous for him
to do that. If it becomes a real viable
alternative to the existing
establishment then it'll be it would be
dangerous for it. So for for him uh yeah
so we'll see about that. All right, with
this brings us to the end of today's
session. So, thank you so much for all
the questions. It was fun. Uh I think um
taking questions from comments I think
it's the best way forward. It ensures
that there is quality
in the ask a widget show. When I simply
take questions from the live chat, uh
there's no guarantee of the quality.
When I take questions for even from the
super chat, there's no guarantee of the
quality. So, I think going forward most
of the times I will do I will take
questions from the comments in future
episodes. Tomorrow I'm going to do a
session in which the live chats in which
the super chats will be turned on. So
let's see how it goes. One more time
I'll try it and then for next week we'll
take a call. Next week some some things
will change and you will see how it
goes. So thank you so much everybody for
your questions and I will see you in
tomorrow's live stream. Hopefully you
all attend it. I look forward to seeing
you there. Thank you very much. Take
care. Keep asking questions. Keep
learning. Keep raising your standards
and I'll see you tomorrow. Bye-bye.